本集内容包含性暴力描述
也许会令一些观众感到不适
六个月
Six months.
我过了六个月才举报玛莎
It had taken me six months to report Martha.
需要帮忙吗?
Can I help you?
我应该从昨天
I should have started with Teri,
玛莎攻击泰瑞的事说起 但我没有
how Martha attacked her just yesterday, but I didn't.
我想报案 流程是怎样的?
I would like to report something. How does it work?
你想报什么案?
What would you like to report?
我该提及她捏我下体的事 但我没有
I should have mentioned the grope, but I didn't.
我不知道该怎么跟你说 但我被人跟踪了
I don't know how to tell you this, but I'm, like... I'm getting stalked.
- 男人还是女人? - 一个女人
- By a man or a woman? - A woman.
我该提起她的名字 那些报道 还有她的前科
I should have mentioned her name, the articles, her previous crimes,
但我偏偏没有
but I just didn't.
听着 我真的很担心
Look, I'm... I'm really worried here.
我觉得她需要帮助
I think she needs help.
- 当警察问起... - 你为什么现在才来报案?
- And when the policeman asked... - Why'd it take you so long to report it?
...那段回忆如潮水般翻涌而至
...it all just came flooding back.
驯鹿宝贝
大约五年前 我去参加了爱丁堡国际艺穗节
About five years earlier, I went to the Edinburgh Festival.
我一直梦想在那里演出
It was always an ambition of mine to take a show there,
走上喧嚣的街头 跟其他表演者和艺人一样
to join the hustle and bustle of street performers and artists
盼望能幸运地一举成名
gambling their luck on a shot at fame.
我知道终有一天 我会来碰碰运气
I knew I had to come here one day and take a chance myself.
写作 表演 喜剧 任何创作形式都可以
Writing, acting, comedy, whatever it took.
我所追求的自由洒脱的生活
I just needed the kind of freedom in life
唯有通过 敢于做梦 勇敢追梦才能实现
which only comes from dreaming big and stopping at nothing to get there.
啤酒花酒吧
所以当我抵达位于城郊的表演场地
So as I arrived at my venue on the outskirts of town
即便一进门就注意到了 肮脏的窗户 黏糊的地板
and noticed the grubby windows, the sticky floors,
还有空气中洋溢的炸薯条的油脂味
the smell of chip fat as I walked in...
我依然满怀憧憬和期待
it felt like everything to me.
- 你好 - 好
- Hello. - Yo.
请问喜剧表演厅怎么走?
Can you let me know where to go for the comedy?
演员还是观众?
Performer or punter?
演员
Performer.
那边的门
Door over there.
谢谢
Thank you.
艺穗节
你指的是另一扇门还是...
Do you mean, like, a different door, or...
角落有插孔 把话筒插上 餐桌推到一边就好
Plug it in in the corner. Shove the table to the side.
什么? 这就是我的舞台? 就在这儿? 在酒吧大厅里?
What? This is my stage? Here? In with the main bar?
没错
That's right.
电视会一直开着吗?
I mean, do the televisions stay on?
我们会调成静音
We mute.
- 那些客人呢? - 你要想的话 可以请他们离开
- And the punters? - You can ask them to leave if you'd like.
不 那我可做不出来
Oh no, I couldn't do that.
他们是这里的常客 而我只来一个月
They're here 12 months a year. I'm only here one.
你能请他们离开吗?
Can you ask them to leave?
不能
No.
话说 他们对搞笑表演有兴趣吗?
I mean, do they even wanna see comedy?
只有一个办法可以知道
Only one way to find out.
好的 那我们就快开始吧 对
All right. We'd better begin. Yeah.
搞什么啊
Come on!
该死的爱丁堡艺穗节
Fucking Edinburgh Fringe!
女士们先生们 大家好 欢迎观看我的搞笑表演
Hello, ladies and gentlemen, welcome to the comedy.
我会在这堵墙后面换演出服
Uh, I'm gonna go behind that little wall there and change.
待会儿我一喊 大家就热情欢迎我上台
When I shout out, you all go mad and welcome me to the stage.
听起来怎么样?
How does that sound?
好极了 有一位回应我
Great. One person.
好的 那我们开始吧
All right, here goes.
女士们先生们 请以热烈的掌声 欢迎
Ladies and gentlemen, please welcome to the stage
唐尼·邓恩上台
Donny Dunn!
好耶 让我听到你们的尖叫
Fucking yes! Let me hear ya! Whoo!
话说我妈今天去世了
So my mum died today.
不是吧? 没反应?
Really? Nothing?
我妈才刚去世 我就以那种方式 作为演出的开场 不好笑吗?
You see, it's funny opening a show like that when my mum has just died, no?
对照修辞法?
Antithesis?
表演结果一塌糊涂
The shows were just awful.
大多数时候 我不得不因为没有观众而取消表演
Most days, I had to cancel due to nobody turning up.
还有一次 我被开单身派对的人
One time, I had to end the show early
当成了戏弄的对象 只好提早结束演出
when I was caught in the crosshairs of a stag do.
- 还给我 嘿  - 来拿呀
- Give that! Hey, hey! - Here!
哎呀 糟了
No, no!
别闹了 拜托  我之后的表演还要用呢
No, please! I need that for the rest of the month.
有时候我会光站着不发传单
Some days, I stood not handing out any flyers
暗自希望这样就不会有人来
in the hope nobody would come.
才刚表演一个星期 我已经感觉自己是演艺界的垃圾了
I was about a week in, and I felt like the dregs of show business.
我前几天刚割了包皮 好不容易才找到足够大的剪刀
Got circumcised the other day. Just had to find scissors big enough.
懂我的意思吗?
Do you know what I mean? Yeah?
我在说我的鸡鸡很大
I'm saying I got a big cock.
没反应? 不好笑? 不是吧? 好吧 没关系
Nothing? No? Really? Okay. That's fine.
有天我去商店买茄子 结果带回了这个
Went to the shops for some eggplant. Came back with this.
见鬼 老板真觉得我好糊弄是吧?
Bloody hell! He saw me coming, didn't he?
对吧? 把蛋粘在盆栽上 跟我说这是小茄子
Yeah? He's just taped some eggs to a plant.
我怀疑就算我提早收拾行李回家了 都不会有人注意到
I questioned if I went home, whether anyone would notice,
更不会有人在意
whether anyone would care.
好了 女士们先生们 表演结束
All right, ladies and gentlemen, that's the show!
我会拿着小桶站在门边
I'm gonna be standing by the door
大家认为这场表演值多少钱 就请随意打赏
with a bucket for your donations. Give what you think the show is worth.
感谢前来
Thanks for coming.
- 扎心了 - 至少比昨天有进步
- Ouch. - Better than yesterday, I suppose.
昨天收获了什么?
What was yesterday?
一颗扣子和一个避孕套
- A button and a condom.
来 我有东西给你
Here, I've got something for you.
不知道从谁钱包里掉出来的
Fell out of someone's wallet last night.
你想要就拿去吧 我知道 你们这些艺术家可喜欢相互吹捧了
It's yours if you want it. I know how much you artistes love to schmooze.
爱丁堡艺穗节 2011
露娜酒吧 贵宾会员酒吧
我们在拍摄时完全没想到它会成功
We had no idea it would ever work when we shot it.
你知道那个有很多锡罐兵的场景吗?
You know the, uh, the scene with the tin-can soldiers?
那是在兰卡斯特的一个沙滩上拍的 我们往演员身上裹了餐饮锡箔纸
We shot that on a beach in Lancaster using tinfoil from catering.
裹得太多 以至于班吉说 他感觉自己的补牙填充物都快脱落了
We used so much that Benji said he could feel his fillings coming out.
不好意思 抱歉打扰了 你参与了《棉口蛇》的制作吗?
Uh, excuse me. Sorry to interrupt, but did you work on Cotton Mouth?
- 对 - 天哪 我超爱那部剧
- Yeah. - Oh my God, I fucking love that show.
- 你负责做什么? - 我是编剧组的
- What did you do on it? - I was on the writing staff.
天哪 我可以膜拜你吗?
Holy shit, do I kiss your feet now?
话说 我最近在啤酒花酒吧演出
Um, look, I'm doing this show up at the Hoppy bar.
有空来看看吧
Come down and see it if you can.
- "《大笑至死》" - 对 这标题很妙吧?
- "LOL on Cancer." - Yeah. Yeah, it's a great title, isn't it?
我们尽量找机会去
We'll try.
你们有看到不错的表演吗?
You guys seen anything decent?
- 回头见 - 好
See you later. - Yeah.
可恶
Fuck.
真是自负的混蛋
Wankers, aren't they?
是啊 但我给人的第一印象也很糟
Yeah, terrible first impression on my part though.
真糟糕 你以后别想在影视圈混了
Shocking. You'll never work in the industry again.
目前为止都还没混过呢
Chance would be a fine thing.
- 看见那边那个人了吗? - 嗯
- See that guy over there? - Yeah.
他是《绵口蛇》的编剧 那部剧特别棒 你看过吗?
He wrote Cotton Mouth. It's fucking amazing. Have you seen it?
- 零星看过一点 不是我的菜 - 那你肯定是疯了
- Bits and bobs. Not my thing. - Then you're mental.
这么年轻就那么成功 简直违法嘛
Should be illegal for people to be that young and that successful.
想在他的酒里下毒吗?
Wanna slip poison in his drink?
天哪 这想法真阴暗
Wow, that's dark.
不过 好呀
But yes.
- 但话说回来 节目成功还是全靠演员 - 完全赞同
- Anyway, the actors made that show. - Couldn't agree more.
天哪 我真恨我自己 那么在乎他的看法
Man, I hate that I care about his opinion.
你是干什么的?
What do you do?
观众笑了 我就是搞笑艺人 观众没笑 我就是行为艺术家
Uh, I'm a comedian when they laugh, a performance artist when they don't.
- 那今晚如何? - 今晚我是行为艺术家
- How were they tonight? - They came for the art.
- 对了 我叫唐尼 - 达瑞安·奥康纳
- Um, I'm Donny, by the way. - Darrien O'Connor.
是那个...
Uh, as in...
《绵口蛇》的编剧
Cotton Mouth.
- 什么? 可刚才那是... - 我的助手
- What? But... But then who's-- - My writing assistant.
但以后不是了 因为我发现他冒用我的头衔
Former writing assistant, now I know he's stealing my job.
真抱歉 先前我说"全靠演员" 是开玩笑的
I'm so sorry. All that actor stuff was merely banter.
我知道你的实力 出色的剧本才是那部剧的精髓
I knew who you were. The writing was the best bit about that show.
- 别担心 没事 - 见鬼...
- Don't worry. Fu...
- 可你刚说不喜欢那部剧 - 确实不喜欢
- You just said you didn't like it. - I don't.
那你为什么要写自己不喜欢的剧?
Why would you do a show that you don't like?
因为我是影视界的妓女 来者不拒
I'm a televisual prostitute. I'll take whatever anyone gives me.
那么失败的搞笑艺人呢?
Well, how about a failing comedian?
女士们先生们 请热烈欢迎
Ladies and gentlemen, please welcome to the stage
那个正在服用 抗焦虑药物的搞笑男人上台...
the man who puts the LOL in propranolol...
麻烦后期把这段剪掉
We'll probably cut that bit.
...唐尼·邓恩
...Donny Dunn!
话说我妈今天去世了
So my mum died today.
这大概正是她希望看到的吧
I guess this is what she would've wanted.
我尬死在台上 下去陪她
Me to die with her.
谁想见见我的朋友珀西?
Um, who wants to meet my friend Percy?
好
Yeah
好的 好 那好
All right. Yeah, okay.
这是珀西 我们是腹语双人组
This is Percy. We're a ventriloquist double act.
嗨 珀西 你好吗?
Hi, Percy, how are you?
我很好 谢谢 你呢?
I'm good, thanks. You?
你今天在忙什么 珀西?
What have you been up to today, Percy?
给人吹箫
Sucking cock.
哇 真慷慨 谢谢
Oh, wow, great. Thank you.
太棒了
Oh, cool!
- 感谢前来 - 再见
- Thanks for coming. - Cheers.
非常感谢
Appreciate that.
- 天哪 20英镑的钞票 - 昨晚有人忘了说再见
- Jesus, a 20. - I didn't get a goodbye last night.
- 所以我想着让他今天补回来 - 对哦 那好 再见
- So I thought I'd come get it now. - Oh, right. Well, uh, goodbye.
不 等等 我开玩笑的 对不起
No. No, wait. I'm joking. Sorry.
你很奇怪
You're strange.
是吗? 见鬼
Am I? Shit.
别担心 我不介意 怪就怪呗
Don't worry. I don't mind a bit of strange.
我们谈谈吧 我可以给你些建议 把表演打磨得更上一层楼
Let's talk. Might have a few pointers how to take this show to the next level.
哇 好 那太好了 好的
Wow. Yeah. I mean... I mean, that would be great, yeah.
- 那就回头见了 - 对 回头见 老兄
- Laters, then. - Yeah. Laters, uh, cowboy.
我在胡说什么啊?
What the fuck?
接下来的几周 达瑞安指导了我的演出
Darrien became involved in the show for the next few weeks,
为我提供建议 哪些内容好笑、哪些不好笑
giving me advice on bits that were and weren't working.
...而且要保持眼神交流
...and maintain eye contact.
花各种时间排练 把演出打磨成型
Rehearsing all kinds of hours to whip everything into shape.
看着我
Look at me.
前面摆三排
Three rows across the front.
很快 酒吧里的电视被关掉 观众席也面向了正确的位置
Soon the televisions were shut off and the chairs faced the right way.
连工作人员也开始往外赶 询问何时播放球赛的客人
Even the bar staff dismissed customers who dared to ask when the football was on.
不 今天不播放球赛 去路那边的酒吧试试吧
No, we're not showing it today. Try the pub down the road.
节目一下子火爆了起来
And the shows just flourished.
女士们先生们 现在有请我们的表演者
Ladies and gentlemen, please welcome to the stage
唐尼·邓恩上台
Donny Dunn!
话说我妈今天去世了
So my mum died today.
对 这大概正是她希望看到的吧
Yeah, I suppose this is what she would have wanted.
我尬死在台上 下去陪她
Me to die with her.
每天晚上 我都会跟达瑞安
Every night, I would go out with Darrien
去城里最大的私人会员酒吧聚会 过着名流般的生活
and live life like a celebrity in the main private members' bar in town,
喝一整晚的鸡尾酒 滔滔不绝地谈论我的表演
drinking cocktails until the early hours, talking endlessly about the show
以及艺穗节结束后的打算
and what we were gonna do with it when the festival was over.
我们得把你的演出搬上伦敦的舞台
We need to get you performing this show in London.
达瑞安跟我以往遇到的人都不同
Darrien was like no one I'd ever met before.
他自称是...
A self-prescribed...
佛教徒 追求开放式恋爱的泛性恋 对高品质奢华生活有独特品位
Buddhist, polyamorous pansexual with a taste for the finer things in life.
才认识不到两周 他就让我大开眼界
Within two weeks of knowing him, he'd opened my eyes
我从来不知道 这个世界是如此精彩刺激
to the kind of excitement I didn't even know existed.
被拴在暖气片上 嘴里塞着情趣口塞
It's hard to yell for help chained to a radiator
真的很难张嘴喊救命
with a ball gag in your mouth.
我们坐在那家私人会员酒吧里 探讨各种深刻的话题
And as we sat in that private members' bar and put the world to rights,
我感觉自己迎来了一股变迁之风
I felt like I was gliding on the winds of change.
仿佛这个男人在我眼前晃动着 一把通往新天地的钥匙
Like this man was dangling some keys to a secret club,
而我只需要握住他的手 接受他的指引
and all I needed to do was take his hand and let him guide me.
我们来这里做什么?
What are we doing in here?
厕所有人巡逻
They patrol the toilets. - Oh.
你以后和我一起写剧本吧
We need to get you writing scripts with me.
好啊 那太棒了
Yeah. That would be amazing, yeah.
- 你准备好了吗? - 做什么都行
- Are you ready? - Ready for anything, yeah.
很好 给
Good. Here.
天哪
Fuck.
好孩子
Good lad.
但好景不长
But all good things come to an end.
你们要是觉得这发网难看 我之前喝醉酒
If you think that's bad, I was so drunk,
还把它套在了阴茎上呢
I ended up putting the hairnet on my penis.
达瑞安提早回了伦敦
Darrien went back to London early,
直到艺穗节结束 都没再联系过我
and I didn't hear from him for the rest of the festival.
也许他去哪里休息或者度假了
Maybe he was taking a break or on holiday somewhere,
但我却有种奇怪的感觉
but it felt strange.
随着传单被扔到一边 海报被撤下
And as the flyers got binned and the posters came down,
电视重新打开 开始播放球赛
the televisions came back on and the football started to play,
我不禁怀疑那一切是否只是黄粱一梦
I questioned whether it was some crazy dream.
它究竟是否真实发生过
Whether it even happened at all.
就是这样
That's it.
体会火焰在血管中流动的感觉
Feel like fire flowing through your veins.
让身体尽情随之舞动
Let it take you where it takes you.
接下来的几个月 我去上了牛津的表演学院
In the months that followed, I went to acting school in Oxford.
还记得当初收到录取通知时 我差点喜极而泣
I remember when I got in, I almost broke down crying with happiness.
但在经历了爱丁堡的那一切之后
But following everything that had happened in Edinburgh
除了有幸在此遇见琪莉
and despite meeting Keeley,
回归学习生活感觉就像走了一步错棋
going back to a life of learning seemed like a misstep.
我穿着体操服练习跳舞 假装自己是一簇火焰...
And as I pranced around in a leotard, pretending to be fire...
做发声练习...
or doing vocal warm-ups...
模仿各种动物
...or mimicking animals
学了各种乱七八糟的事 就是没真正学到表演
and basically doing anything other than fucking acting,
内心滋生出一种难以言喻的感觉
I felt one of those impossible-to-articulate feelings
令我不安
in my stomach.
我想念达瑞安
I missed Darrien.
想念他带给我的勇气 他让我感觉自己不再是个边缘人
I missed the confidence he gave me, the feeling of relevancy,
他给了我希望 让我相信有朝一日 我能够有所成就
of hope that one day my life might actually lead somewhere.
而现在 我被淹没在黑色的人群中 犹如沧海一粟
Now, a body in a sea of black, I felt like a nobody again,
我才刚初尝世界的精彩 就再次变回了一个无名小卒
like I was shrinking from the world just as I developed a taste for it.
唐尼
Donny.
来吗?
Coming?
好
Yeah.
达瑞安
抱歉 我得接个电话
I'm sorry, I gotta take this.
你还好吗 伙计?对
All right, mate? Yeah.
很高兴接到你的电话
No, it's great to hear from you.
对 不 我很喜欢 我还挺享受的
Yeah. Yeah, no, I'm... I'm... I'm loving it. I'm really enjoying myself.
那个 我们能换个时间再聊吗? 其实我现在正在上课
Um, look, is there a better time to chat? I'm actually in class right now.
什么? 你是认真的吗? 你想跟我一起写剧本?
What? Are you serious? You want me to write with you?
好啊 伙计 我一百个愿意 当然好了...
I mean, yes, mate. A thousand yeses. Of course. I mean--
唐尼 你在搞什么啊? 老师快气炸了
Donny, what are you playing at? She's fucking raging in there.
好 我马上回去
Yeah, I'll be two seconds, okay? I'll be two seconds.
我得先挂了 但是好的 就这么定了
Look, I've gotta go, but yes, 100%.
唐尼·布拉斯科
Donnie Brasco.
希妮德·奥康娜
Sinéad O'Connor.
很高兴再见到你 一切还好吗?
It's good to see you. You all right?
好着呢 进来吧
Yeah. Come in.
谢谢 好
Thanks, yeah.
哇 这地方真不错
Wow, this place is amazing.
天啊 你养了只猫
Oh, wow, you've got a cat.
弗格斯 我们非常相爱
Fergus. We're very much in love.
我毫不意外
I'm not surprised.
你真是个可爱的小家伙 对吧 弗格斯? 你好呀 伙计
You're a lovely little fella, aren't you, Fergus? Hello, mate.
要不要喝杯茶?
Cup of tea?
好的 其实我写了几场戏
Okay, so I've actually written up a few scenes and stuff.
随便写的 尚待改进
Um, nothing major. Still needs a bit of work.
好吧
All right.
有60页呢
Sixty pages.
对 没花多少时间
Yeah, didn't take long.
这样吧
I tell you what.
你来给我介绍故事梗概 正好练习一下推销自己的作品
Why don't you give me the gist? Be a good lesson in pitching.
好吧 故事的主人翁 是一个名叫奈吉尔的人
Okay, well, it's about this guy called Nigel,
他是个非常成功的律师 在50岁那年
a high-flying lawyer who decides, at the age of 50,
他决定尝试职业摔跤
to try his hand at professional wrestling.
这个题材很小众
That's quite niche.
是吗?
Really?
对 除了六岁小孩 谁还会看摔跤啊?
Yeah. Who watches wrestling anymore who's above the age of six?
是啊 不 反正我不看
Yeah, no. Not me anyway.
继续吧
Continue.
总之 基本上就是 他忽然爱上了摔跤 然后越来越投入
Anyway, basically, he gets the bug, and he starts wrestling more and more.
很快他就难以维持 工作和爱好之间的平衡
Soon he is struggling to keep the balance between his two worlds.
他开始顶着被打得青紫的眼圈出庭
He starts, like, turning up to court cases with black eyes,
有时候他忘记卸妆就去...
or he... he's forgotten to take his makeup off and, um...
所以他必须做出抉择
Well, so he has this choice to make.
是以律师的身份生活下去
Live his life as a lawyer
还是做刽子手哈利
or Hangman Harry,
那个来自德州奥斯汀 脚踏污泥 豪饮啤酒的酒馆狂野拳击手
the mud-stompin', beer-swillin', bar-room brawler from Austin, Texas.
刽子手哈利是他给自己取的名号
Hangman Harry is his wrestling name.
仍需打磨
Needs more work.
可你还没看过呢
Oh, but you... you haven't read it.
等你说动我了 我会看的
I'll read it when you sell it to me.
我可以去另一个房间 试着...
I could sit in another room and try--
你想嗑药吗?
Do you wanna get high?
- 在这里? - 对 有何不可呢?
- What, here? Yeah, why not?
晚点我们还可以出去喝一杯 就像在爱丁堡时一样
We can go out and grab a drink later. Be like Edinburgh all over again.
好啊
Yeah, sure.
天哪 你和一些喜剧界的传奇人物合作过啊
Holy shit, you've worked with some comedy legends.
- 他们怎么样? - 一般般
- What are they like? - Average.
开什么玩笑? 他们都超厉害的
No, you can't mean that. They're amazing.
其中有几个还在我 "社交晚宴最想邀请的人"里排前五呢
I mean, some of them would be in my top five dinner-party guests for sure.
你玩过那个游戏吗?
Ever played that game?
你可以邀请任何人来吃晚餐 但只能选五个人
You can invite anyone you want for dinner, but you can only pick five.
听起来很糟糕 我的家是一个神圣的地方
Ugh, sounds horrible. My home's a sacred space.
只有很特别的人才能来
Takes someone very special to be allowed in.
拜托 别回避问题 你会选哪五个人?
Come on, that's a cop-out answer. Who would they be?
我不会选名人
Well, they wouldn't be celebrities.
只会选领袖人物 宗教大师 这类灵性觉醒的人
They'd be leaders, gurus, spiritually awake.
或者干脆就好几个不同版本的我
That, or me around each place.
太扯...六个你一起开派对 天哪 我都能想象你们会嗑多少药了
Six of you at one party. Jesus, I can imagine how many drugs there'd be.
告诉你我的人选吧
I'll tell you mine.
热维斯 萨莎·拜伦·科恩 茱莉亚·戴维斯
Gervais, Sacha Baron Cohen, Julia Davis,
库根或者普赖尔 再加上一个圣雄甘地之类的人
Coogan or Pryor, and, I don't know, Gandhi or someone
来彰显我品德高尚
because you need to look virtuous.
- 你还想再爽一点吗? - 好啊
- Do you wanna get really high? - Fuck yeah.
不 我是指会爽翻天那种
No, like, really high.
来吧
Fuck yeah.
- 对了 他们的秘诀是什么? - 什么意思?
- What was their secret, by the way? What do you mean?
他们是如何取得今天的成就的?
What did they all do to get where they are today?
他们听我的话
Listen to me.
没跟你开玩笑
I'm serious.
对于我的所有要求 他们都全情投入
They threw themselves into everything I asked of them.
哇 真了不起
Wow, that's... that's awesome.
过来 坐到我旁边
Here. Come sit next to me.
这都是些什么?
What's all this?
这是莫利
This is a bomb of MDMA.
这是液态摇头丸 一种松弛剂
And this is GHB. It's a relaxant.
- 它能让你放松 - 好
- It relaxes you. - Yeah.
相信我 这会是你前所未有的经历
Trust me. You haven't experienced anything like it.
遇见你就是我前所未有的经历 这点毋庸置疑
I haven't experienced anything like you, that's for sure.
见鬼 好恶心
Fucking hell. That's disgusting.
有付出才有收获嘛
Little pain for a little gain.
第一次嗑嗨真的是前所未有的体验
The first time I came up was like nothing I'd ever experienced.
仿佛有一束圣光从天而降
It felt like a beam of divine light shone down from space,
穿透达瑞安家的屋顶 照进客厅
through Darrien's roof and into his living room,
将我瞬间笼罩
exactly where I was sitting,
那光芒如同印度洋温暖的海浪 冲刷着我的身体
as warm Indian Ocean waves passed up and down my body.
靠在那张沙发上 达瑞安说我的才华
And on that couch, Darrien spoke about my talents
毫不逊色于我崇拜的任何喜剧巨匠
in the same vein as all my comedy heroes growing up.
你是个很有前途的年轻人
You've got a big future ahead of you.
前途无量
A very big future.
他的每一句话和我吸入的每一口药物
With every sentence he said and every drug I took,
都令我对此深信不疑 我仿佛能够闻到 甚至尝到
I started to believe it, smell it,
成功的喜悦
taste it, even.
我的梦想化作了一幅画卷
That my dreams were quantifiable.
在我眼前徐徐展开 是那样的触手可及
That I could almost grasp them as they untangled before me.
别再浪费时间等待了
No time to wait around.
你不介意吧?
You don't mind, do you?
不介意
No.
见鬼
Oh shit.
怎么了?
What?
你怎么了?
What's wrong?
我想吐
I think I'm gonna puke.
不 别吐在猫碗里
No. Not in the cat bowl.
你还好吧?
You okay?
我给你拍拍背
Let me pat your back. - Oh,
谢谢 真不好意思
thank you. I'm so sorry.
天啊 真对不起
Oh God. I'm so sorry.
住手
Stop!
喝杏仁奶可以吗?
Will almond milk do?
给 喝下去就舒服多了
There you go. That'll sort you out.
刚才的事 我很抱歉
I'm really sorry about that.
没关系 下次我们慢慢来
It's okay. We'll go slower next time.
我真想假装一切到那晚就结束了
I would love to pretend that's as far as it went.
达瑞安来电
嘿 伙计 最近怎么样?
Hey, mate. How's it going?
对 不 我很好
Yeah. Yeah. No, I'm... I'm... I'm... I'm good.
我要去上课了 所以如果...
Look, I'm about to go into class, so if it--
什么?
What?
什么?那个电视台 读了《刽子手哈利》?
What? The channel have Hangman Harry?
天哪 他们喜欢吗? 那真是...
Holy shit. They love it? That's fucking...
是啊 太不可思议了 我...
Yeah, yeah, that... that's incredible. I...
喔 你想让我...
Oh, you want me to--
对 不 有道理
Yeah, yeah. Yeah, yeah. No, that makes sense.
是啊 不 当然 好的 我一定来
Yeah. No, sure, yeah. I'll come.
- 这是天大的机会呀 - 是啊 太棒了 谢谢你
- That's huge. - Yeah. That's great. Thank you.
在职业生涯初期 就能得到主流频道的支持
To have a massive channel backing you this early in your career.
达瑞安向我阐述电视台的反馈时
Darrien took me through everything the channel said,
我笑得合不拢嘴
and I beamed from ear to ear
他讲到了整季剧本的佣金 期权协议的时限
as he spoke of series commissions and option periods
还有一大堆不明觉厉的概念
and all these fabulous things I didn't understand,
以至于当他把药物拿出来时 我毫不犹豫地就吃了
that by the time he cracked out the drugs, I said yes without hesitation.
我还以为我搞砸了
I thought I'd blown it, you know.
搞砸什么?
What?
这一切
This.
我上回吐的时候
When I threw up.
别傻了
Don't be silly.
只是吐了一下 还不至于让我弃置你的才华
It'd take a lot more than vomit for me to be put off with your talents.
谢谢你
Thank you.
真的很感谢
Thank you so much.
如果有什么我能做的...
If there's anything I can do...
只要...坚持梦想就好
Just... keep dreaming.
这个简单
That's easy.
跟琪莉一起搬到伦敦后
After I'd moved to London with Keeley,
我几乎每个周末都会去达瑞安家嗑药
I started taking drugs at Darrien's house almost every weekend.
来 我们照例从莫利开始
Here. We'll start off with the usual MDMA.
我盲目地相信着他许下的承诺
I had fully drunk the Kool-Aid of his promises,
相信着成功指日可待
of believing that success was right around the corner.
我会在30岁前拥有属于自己的节目
That I would have my own show by 30.
除此之外 还会成为百万富翁
A millionaire around the same time.
我对他所说的深信不疑
All stuff he said to me
任由他把最新的化学品送到我嘴里
before he spoon-fed me the latest chemical.
只偶尔吸食过大麻的我 已然演变成
I went from a guy who had smoked a bit of weed
整周沉迷于毒品 吸食霹雳可卡因...
to week-long benders, high on crack.
别害怕 追逐无与伦比的快感
Chase the high. Don't be scared.
...还有冰毒...
And meth.
你会充分发挥自己的创造潜能
You'll embrace your creative potential.
...和海洛因
And heroin.
你会大有作为的
You're going places.
吸食了足够多的药物 你会进入一种状态
When you take enough to reach that plane
所有思绪停止 快感侵袭而至
where all thought stops and euphoria begins,
那些关于 未来 名利和幸福的高谈阔论
talk of the future and fame and happiness
变得无比真实 正如此刻体内流动着的种种化学品
feel almost as real as the chemicals that flow through your body.
毫无疑问 如今在我看来 成功只是时间问题
It was only a matter of time now, surely.
有很多次 我都在他眼前昏睡过去
I passed out many times in his company.
通常醒来时 都会发现他躺在我旁边
I would often wake to find him lying next to me,
而他的手和嘴 探索着我各个不同的身体部位
his hands and mouth in various places as he searched around my body.
当我跌跌撞撞地走向浴室 会发现下体上凝结着
I would stumble to the bathroom and find his putrid spit
他散发出腐臭味的呕吐物
congealed around my genital area.
然后每到周一 他又会变回那个冷酷严苛的指导者
Then every Monday he was back to his cold, callous self,
毫不留情地批判我的剧本 让我重写 不付酬劳
giving me brutal script notes and making me do overnight rewrites
不顾及我的药劲仍未消退
on a comedown, for no money,
以及最近因为咽喉感染而一直咳嗽
while I coughed up my latest throat infection.
但我仍会回去找他
And still I went back.
- 你不陪我过生日吗? - 不 我跟你说了要去达瑞安家
- You're not spending my birthday with me? - No, I'm going round Darrien's.
搞什么啊 唐尼? 你不觉得这样有点奇怪吗?
What the hell, Donny? Is this not a little bit strange to you?
我不想跟你的朋友一起出去玩 开销太大了
I don't wanna go away with your friends. I can't fucking afford it.
所以你就跑去一个编剧大叔家里嗑药
So instead you're going to an old writer's house to take drugs.
我知道这在你看来很荒谬 但他在帮我开展事业
I know it doesn't make sense to you. But he's helping me with my career.
他帮了你什么? 你搬来伦敦后就一直在酒吧打工
What's he done? You've worked in a bar since you came to London.
- 还有免费给他做事 - 我没时间跟你谈这个
- You do everything for him for free. - I don't have time for this conversation.
那天晚上 达瑞安给我准备了迷幻药
That night, Darrien presented me with acid.
我吃半根 剩下的一根半归你
I'll take half of one. You take one and a half.
放心吧 之后我会引导你
I'll act as your guide so you feel safe.
诀窍就是让身心随着音乐律动
Let the music take you where it wants to.
有时候 当别人问我
I sometimes think back to this image,
"你是怎么走上喜剧这条路的?"
me, mid-twenties, sitting high as a kite,
我会回想起这个画面
watching this 55-year-old man
二十多岁的我 坐在那里飘飘欲仙
dancing this odd Amazonian jig in front of me,
看这个55岁的男人
when somebody asks me the question,
在我面前跳古怪的亚马逊舞蹈
"How did you get into comedy?"
继续描述你看见了什么
Keep telling me what you're seeing.
缤纷摇曳的色彩 似乎...描绘着什么形状
Shimmering colors. The... outline of something.
所以我现在是凤凰了?
So I'm a phoenix right now?
你看到的是这样吗?
Is that what you're seeing?
你得把我视为某种强大的个体
It's important that you see me as something strong.
一只凤凰 一位骑士
A phoenix. A knight.
或者某个你喜欢的摔跤手
Maybe one of those wrestlers that you like.
忽然间 没来由地
Suddenly, seemingly from nowhere,
一个清晰 强烈的念头 在我的脑海浮现
this clear, strong thought entered my head.
-"他在试图操控你的思想" - 怎么了?
-"He's trying to control your mind." - What's wrong?
"这个男人很坏 这个情况很糟 快逃"
"This man is bad. This situation is bad. Get out now."
可恶
Fuck!
- 见鬼  - 怎么了?
- Fuck! - What's the matter?
你不舒服吗?
What's wrong?
我看不见了 眼前只有白茫茫一片
I can't see. All I can see is white.
没事 你正在重生
It's fine. It's fine. It's rebirth.
- 我看不见 我他妈看不见了 - 有我在 你很安全
- I can't see. I can't fucking see. - You're safe with me.
这段时间一直被我压抑的潜意识
My subconscious, that I'd been repressing this entire time,
终于跳出来向我揭示了现状的不堪
had reared its head to shine the most obvious light on a fucked-up situation.
你怎么了?
What's happening to you?
- 这很糟糕 我听见有人说这很糟糕 - 那是你的幻觉
- This is bad. I'm being told this is bad. - It's paranoia.
- 对抗它 - 关掉音乐
- Fight against it. - Turn the music off.
已经关掉了
It's off, it's off.
见鬼
Agh, fuck!
Fuck!
该死
Oh fuck!
这该死的... 天哪 这该死的音乐
The fucking... Oh God! The fucking music!
可恶
Agh, fuck!
把这个喝了
Have this.
- 不要 - 会有助于缓解不适
- No. - It'll help take the edge off.
你以前喝过的 它能帮你放松
You've had it before. It relaxes you.
不 尽量别吐出来
No. No, try to keep it in.
吞下去
Swallow. Swallow.
很好
That's good. That's good.
药劲太强了
That was strong! That was strong!
好了
Okay. Okay.
There.
对着我的手呼气 调整呼吸
Breathe into my hand. Breathe.
没事的
It's okay.
这是必经的过程
It's okay. This is part of it.
都是过程而已
It's all part of it.
放松
Relax.
放轻松
没事的
It's fine.
不
No.
不要
昨晚感觉如何?
How'd you find it?
你该去冲个澡 用温水清洗一下对你有好处
You should shower. A wash in warm water will do you good.
见鬼
Fuck!
我能进来吗?
Can I come in?
过来
Come here.
我很想说我一走了之了
I would love to say I left.
我夺门而出 再也没回去 但其实在那之后 我又逗留了数日
That I stormed out and never went back. But I stayed for days afterwards.
事实上 周一我的眼睛感染发炎
In fact, come Monday, I got an eye infection
于是躺在他家地板上 让他用盐水帮我洗眼睛
and lay on his floor as he bathed it in salt water.
到了周二 他忙着接电话时 我就帮他喂猫
On Tuesday, I fed his cat while he took phone calls.
直到周三 我终于回家了
On Wednesday, I finally went home.
嘿 你怎么啦?
Hey, what's wrong?
没什么 就是之前 跟你闹得不欢而散 太难过了
Oh, nothing. I just feel bad for how we left things.
最让我在意的就是那些未知
What bothered me most was the not knowing.
在我昏睡不醒的期间都发生了什么?
What happened all those moments I passed out?
你没事吧?
Are you okay?
我没事 对
Yeah. Yeah, I'm fine. Yeah.
过往种种 是他真心认为我有才华 还是一场精心策划的操控?
Did he ever believe in me, or was this whole thing preplanned manipulation?
他从头到尾都是清醒的吗?
Was he sober the entire time?
那么做对他有什么好处? 仅仅出于使人堕落的欲望吗?
And what was he getting from it? Was it simply a desire to corrupt?
为了满足他病态的心理 实现某种目标?
To achieve whatever his sick mind wanted to achieve?
摧毁我的生活会让他性致勃发?
Was that the turn-on, to ruin my life?
要不我们去看电视吧? 我找不到感觉
Uh, look, do you wanna watch something instead? I'm... I'm not feeling it.
不要 闭嘴
No, shut up.
对不起 今天恐怕是不行了
I... I... I'm sorry. It's... it's... it's just not happening today.
- 昨天也是这样 - 也许我需要一段冷静期
- It didn't happen yesterday either. - Maybe I need to take a break from it all.
你指的是做爱还是我们的关系?
What? A break from sex or from me?
天哪
Wow.
好吧
Okay.
琪莉搬走后 我陷入了崩溃
After Keeley moved out, I fell to pieces.
我能做的就只剩下审视那段回忆
Now all that was left to do was stare at the memory of what happened.
我开始对自己的性倾向感到困惑 那种困惑
I started to feel this overwhelming sexual confusion
如潮水般将我淹没
crashing through my body.
我以为它会自行退去 但它却演变成了不自信
I thought it might pass, but it became an insecurity,
在我的内心不断蔓延 直至疯狂肆虐
which grew into a raging madness within me.
我无从分辨这些感受是因他而起
I could never tell whether these feelings were because of him
还是一直以来 隐藏在我内心深处的真实
or whether they always existed deep down.
是我在无意间散发出的某种气质 导致了那一切的发生
Did it all happen because I was giving off some vibe I wasn't aware of?
还是那一切的发生 导致我变成了这样?
Or did what happen make me this way?
我走在街上 会感觉所有人都在看我
I would feel like everyone who looked at me
他们能看穿我经历的一切
could see what I was going through.
仿佛他们在窥探我的灵魂时
Like they were peering into my soul,
看见了我被性侵的经历 以及我的怀疑和困惑
seeing the rape and the doubts and the confusion.
好像我的双眼是两扇窗户
Like my eyes were these windows
透过它们能看见我人生中 隐藏最深的秘密
onto the most tightly-held secret of my life.
我会幻想自己杀死他
I would dream of killing him,
切掉他的阴茎或者割了他的舌头 怎样杀伤力最大就怎么来
chopping his cock off or his tongue out, whichever had done me the most damage,
然后把他的尸体烧成灰烬
and burning his body to the ground.
于是 在历经数月的 仇恨 愤怒和困惑之后
So after months of hate and anger and confusion,
我已经别无选择
I was left with no choice.
极端性爱
见鬼
fuck.
我很快就高潮了
I orgasmed quickly,
快到我再也无法否认 我的性取向发生了转变
in such a way that there was no denying my desires were shifting.
我每天都会情不自禁地打开电脑
Every day, the laptop called me to it.
我感到无比地困惑和恼怒
I felt confused. I felt angry.
就如同重新经历了一次青春期
I felt like I was going through puberty all over again.
好的 来吧
Okay, yeah, yeah, yeah.
我开始跟不同性别的人乱搞
I started having reckless sex with people of all genders
绝望地追寻着真相
in this desperate pursuit of the truth.
我将自己置于淫乱不堪的境地 甚至甘冒再次被强暴的风险
I would put myself in fucked-up situations where I'd almost risk being raped again
试图理解当初被侵犯的来龙去脉
in this attempt to understand the first time.
若我像个男妓一样被人轮番取乐
Like if I'm passed around like a whore,
或许我至少能说服自己 不去在乎这具躯体
then I might at least shed this idea that my body is part of me somehow.
谁在乎以前发生过什么呀?
Like who cares if it happened before?
如今那种事已上演了无数次 过往如何根本无关紧要
It's happened a ton of times now, so what does it matter?
但其实它很重要
But it mattered.
它很重要 因为这一切正是他想要的
It mattered because this is what he wanted.
这正是一直以来他眼中的我
This is what he saw in me all along.
一种苦涩的感觉涌上心头 令我如鲠在喉
Then a feeling so bitter I could almost catch it in my throat.
那就是事实似乎证明了他是对的
That he'd been vindicated somehow.
我犹如一头困兽
Now I was stuck,
被一群混迹酒吧的 厌女的异性恋正统主义者包围
surrounded by pilsner misogynists so heteronormative
除了寻求他们的认同 我什么也做不了
I could do nothing but crave their approval.
那天恰好碰上前所未有的暴风雨
It was the stormiest weather.
我去过马略卡岛很多次 它真的很美
So many times I've been to Mallorca. It's beautiful.
如果你购买全包套餐 就可以...
You can have these all-inclusive things where you just...
一切都是免费的 全部
Everything is for free. Like, everything.
我同时跟十几个人约会和交往
Dates and relationships by the dozen.
这一切都源自于那次最黑暗的经历
All of which started off in the gutter of what happened.
...但我还是想坚持采用...
...but I think I'm gonna stick with...
我对恋爱没兴趣 我已经失去了爱人的能力
I wasn't interested in love. I had no capacity for it anymore.
我只期望这些人能带给我答案
I just wanted these people to provide fucking answers.
你知道吗? 在马略卡岛 他们会问你想不想做水上韵律操
You know in Mallorca, when they ask if you want to do aqua aerobics?
其实没必要不停问我的...
You don't need to ask me five million times--
不好意思 抱歉 我得去趟洗手间
Excuse me, sorry. Can I... I'm just gonna nip to the bathroom.
我去去就回 好吗?
I'll be right back, yeah?
但我又抛弃和疏远了他们每一个人
As I spurned and alienated every single one of them.
你可以来个360度急转弯 在车轮的刺耳摩擦声中绝尘而去
You could do a 360, screech around the place, just zoom off.
现在很多人都回归胶片拍摄了
A lot of people, they've gone back to shooting film now.
但我还是想坚持采用数码拍摄
I think I'm just gonna stick to digital.
直到我遇见了...
Until I met...
嘿
Hey.
你真人比视频里更帅
You're cuter in person than you are online.
老实说 有好几次我跟人线下约会
Honestly, some of the dates I've been on,
来赴约那些家伙居然 比个人资料照片上的老了15岁
the guys turn up 15 years older than their profile picture.
她具备我梦寐以求的一切 拥有我欠缺的所有素质
She was everything I wanted. Everything I needed.
聪颖 风趣 自信 坚强
Smart, funny, confident, strong.
今晚跟我回家吧
Come back with me tonight.
可每当她握住我的手或者凝望我时
But with every hand-hold or lingering stare
一股强烈的愤怒和羞愧感 就会席卷而至
came a crushing sense of anger and shame
因为我爱上了她
that I was falling in love with her,
我不能再继续隐姓埋名了
that I couldn't hide in anonymity anymore.
只是别告诉托尼
Just don't tell Tony.
也许最令我痛苦的是
And, perhaps most bitter of all,
若非因为那个人的所作所为 我可能根本不会爱上她
that I might not feel this way if he hadn't done what he did.
但当玛莎出现时
But when Martha turned up,
那些困惑逐渐淡去...
all that confusion faded...
她似乎不费吹灰之力地
as she reached, seemingly without effort,
就触及了我内心最不安的角落 然后用光明驱散了黑暗
into the darkest pockets of my insecurity and turned them to light.
你这样完美的骨相简直违法嘛
Should be illegal to have your bone structure too.
他们真该向你收税 男人税
They should tax you for it. Man tax.
玛莎眼中的我 正是我内心渴望成为的样子
Martha saw me the way I wanted to be seen.
所以在走进警局的那一刻
So when it came to the point of going to the police,
我实在无法忍受自己要举报的 是玛莎而不是他 这是何其讽刺啊
I just couldn't stand the irony of reporting her but not him.
需要帮忙吗?
Can I help you?
我总感觉她其实是病了 她身不由己
There was always a sense that she was ill, that she couldn't help it,
而那个男人才是 极端恶劣 擅长思想控制的诱奸犯
whereas he was a pernicious, manipulative groomer.
承认被她侵犯就得承认被他侵犯
To admit to her was to admit to him.
而我还没对任何人坦白过那段经历
And I hadn't admitted him to anyone yet.
- 所以当警察问起... - 你为什么现在才来报案?
- So when the policeman asked... - Why'd it take you so long to report it?
我不知道
I don't know.
你先回家吧 去查看她的邮件
Go home, look through her emails,
找到有特别意义的内容再回来
and when you find something of significance, come back.
在那之前 除非出现有说服力的证据
Until then, unless we see some proper evidence,
否则我们爱莫能助
there's nothing we can do.
在那一刻 我又回到了原点
And with that, I was back to square one.
若你或你认识的人曾遭遇性暴力
请访问以上网站
寻求相关信息 以及在危机时能够求助的资源
根据理查德·加德的话剧 《驯鹿宝贝》改编